Yes, prof.
>> [snorts]
>> Okay, everybody. Good morning.
And
welcome to this lecture on transformers.
Uh today's lecture will will be
taken by Guru Sriram, one of our own.
Guru is currently an ML engineer at
WaybAI.
But he was he's graduated from CMU and
he's been our TA in the past and
continues to be a volunteer
uh even after long after he graduated.
So, I am very thankful to him for doing
this lecture. With that, I'd like to
hand over to Guru Guru. The floor is
yours.
Hello everyone.
Uh really nice to
really uh seems really weird to be on
this uh end of the
room. Usually, I'm
uh well like uh kind of basking in uh
professor's uh
glory.
But uh yeah, so uh my name is Guru. I am
I've been a TA for 2 year 2 semesters
and I'm currently serving as a volunteer
TA.
Uh and uh in about uh 3 hours, I start a
new role as a machine learning engineer
for WaybAI
where uh we where I'll primarily be
working on uh developing small language
models for um
uh enterprise applications for on-edge
deployment. And uh yeah, it kind of
feels uh poetic to be
delivering this uh lecture uh right
before I start since this course played
such a big part in uh
uh for me landing the role.
So, um
especially this lecture. So, uh today
we'll be talking about uh transformers
and uh some of the uh new more modern uh
advancements since the original uh 2017
uh paper.
And [clears throat]
uh
so towards that end, uh we'll be
exploring like uh we'll be starting from
the uh limitations that the RNNs
initially had and then uh we'll go over
a with a little bit of depth to things
like attention and the uh 2017 uh
uh transformer architecture vanilla
transformer architecture that was
introduced and is what you will be uh
implementing for your homework four.
Uh we will then look at uh some of the
more uh modern variants of the uh
transformer
and [snorts] uh look at some uh new
efficiency uh tricks to kind of overcome
uh some of the bottlenecks that the
transformer architecture has
and then we'll also explore um
uh going beyond uh text in and see how
the transformer uh architecture was
applied to uh different modalities and
we'll also look into things like
fine-tuning because
often uh training transformers from the
ground up is something beyond our scope
and
there have been methods that have been
developed to still leverage these uh
large language models for your personal
use through things like fine-tuning.
Right?
So, yeah, here is
uh
uh here's the uh
map of what the lecture will be like on
the nutshell.
And
before we get started
So,
I believe uh we covered a little bit of
this. So,
initially, we started with uh recurrent
neural networks. These were the uh go-to
architecture for sequence modeling for
about like uh 20 years before the
transformer model hit the scene,
probably more.
So, uh on the screen here, we have
visualized uh encoder-decoder
RNN, which is currently doing
uh
um neural machine translation from
French to English, right? So, we have uh
these sequence of words which are being
uh converted to
uh so the classic um
um the classic RNN
I'm sure have been uh really used to by
now is that uh every uh hidden step
every hidden state uh at a
uh at time step t in an RNN depends on
the input embedding at the current time
step and uh
the uh hidden states at the previous
time steps, right?
And then uh so we have the encoder
uh and then the um
the hidden state at the last time step,
the time step t,
uh is this uh fixed-length uh context
vector, uh which is essentially uh
viewed as like the uh summarized
represent a summarized representation of
the entire source sequence. And then the
decoder uh conditions upon uh this
context vector
uh and its own uh previous hidden states
and input embeddings to uh generate uh
things on the target side.
Right? So, this is uh something that
we've been doing uh in both your
assignments and has
previous lectures.
But uh this uh fixed-length uh context
vector vector uh from the source side
that the decoder conditions on is uh
uh information bottleneck, right? So, uh
this uh so let's say you have Now, it
this might not be a big issue for like a
small uh
for for a small translation like this
where we're only translating from like
four words to like
seven words, but imagine imagining
imagine you are like uh translating a
paragraph or something, right? So, like
you had like um maybe 50 words, 100
words and then uh something uh that
started the paragraph, a word that
starts the paragraph uh somehow affects
the uh word uh that ends it.
Um so, this uh like a 124-dimensional
embedding might be too much compression
and might not be uh
might not have enough might not encode
enough information to be uh useful on
the target side. So, this was one of the
uh information bottlenecks that uh RNNs
had.
Right? So,
so one of the first issues with uh RNNs
were like uh there was this there was
this uh long-range uh dependency
problem. So, uh despite like the gating
mechanisms that uh were
introduced by its
uh more uh gated the gating variants
like LSTMs to uh preserve information
across steps,
uh the uh gradients in the neural
network were still uh prone to be uh
prone to diluting towards the uh future
time steps. They were also That's that
was the classic vanishing gradient
problem. They're also uh prone to uh
explode uh due to the uh series of uh
sequential uh steps. So, effectively,
the path length uh of communication
between uh a token uh token one to uh
the token at the end is essentially uh O
of N.
So, if like word one wants to talk to
like word 100, it would like uh take uh
99 steps of uh computation and then the
signal has to survive like uh 99 steps
of like uh transformation uh to be able
to be uh visible to to be able to be
talked to the uh uh token at the end,
right?
So,
um
uh so besides that, there's the other
The other issue is that uh the uh
the recurrent nature of RNNs kind of
forces uh language to be uh thought of
in this uh strict uh sequential chain,
uh but that's not usually how uh we
interpret. So, language
interdependencies in between uh words in
a language might have a might have a
more of a graph-based structure, but
then um even with like um
bidirectional RNNs, you're essentially
like forcing some sort of uh like a
linear uh
uh a strict linear chain.
And then the other problem was the uh
lack of uh parallelizability, right? So,
inherently, uh RNNs have
uh sequential uh dependency.
Uh a hidden state at time step t cannot
be uh be computed until you have
computed uh the hidden state at uh time
step t one minus one.
So, this also results in the GPU
underutilization problem where modern
GPUs are designed to be doing these uh
massively uh parallel uh operations,
but uh essentially, RNNs are uh forcing
them to uh work in this like uh
synchronous manner,
uh which uh does not scale well would
not scale well to like uh training these
uh massive uh data set like uh the
entire data of the entire web.
Right?
So, how did we solve this problem?
Well, we solved this problem by allowing
the decoder to be able to talk to and
look at all the hidden representations
on the encoder side.
Right? So,
that was uh the our initial
um
attempt at attention per se. So, you
would uh take the
uh target embedding on the encoder side
for a token. You would uh
you would compute a dot product
uh with each of the hidden states on the
we can use these. So, as you can see, so
for in this
in this particular time step, start
for some reason um
has a is highly reliant on ill on the
source side. So,
so you can use this like distribution
this attention distribution to take like
a weighted sum of the encoder states,
which can then become your context
vector instead of the
old fixed-sized
last time step hidden state vector you
had before.
And now this context now you can
condition on this context vector and
your
input embedding on the source side to do
your generation. And you can do this for
each time step.
So, what this effectively allows
is for all
for is is for the entire target side and
the entire decoder to have access to all
the um
hidden states on the uh
source side.
Right?
That was the initial attempt at
attention, right?
So, what was the advantage of this,
right? So,
there's no longer a of and Portland.
Every token could directly speak with
has direct access to every token on the
source side.
Um
So, this would this would eliminate the
information decay.
Each uh uh token on the source side on
the target side can uh
based on its values determine how
important
the what hidden state is on the source
side.
And
so, not not this part in particular, but
we'll also see how this also enabled the
removal of this sequential bottleneck.
So, the
the competition is no longer
sequential and
there's
this enabling of this massive massively
paralyzes paralyzed the competition by
GPUs.
Um
Yeah, so this
because of
this
this dynamic gating technology,
there was this
thought that do we need recurrence at
all, right? So,
I believe this is the
a breakthrough that eventually led to
the uh
led to transformers.
The fact that a recurrence is not really
inherent requirement of sequence
modeling that instead of like just
passing a hidden state forward, we could
just keep everything and let the model
decide how much
let let the model look at the entire
sequence
at once and sort of
dynamically figure out like which tokens
it wants to which tokens it finds more
relevant than the other.
Yep, and then when you have when
recurrence is no longer
required, this
down the road leads to also leads to the
sequential bottleneck being
disappeared.
Right? So, that brings us to the
transformer architecture.
The famous 2017 paper by Vaswani
et al, which sort of transfer which sort
of like
is present in all the major models that
you currently see in your life from
Gemini to ChatGPT.
Um this the architecture kind of looks
really complicated, but after all the
inception ResNets and the
SE ResNets that you guys have been
building from homework two,
this architecture compared to those this
architectures kind of piece of cake.
It's pretty much like a pipeline of like
tokenization to vector vector grading
vector embeddings, adding positions, and
then then basically several repeated
repeated chains of like the attention
competition being
added being um
operated on in like various different
ways.
And an MLP,
which then finally leads to then you
have this final one final linear layer
to transform into the vocabulary space
and you get the output probabilities.
But we'll be going through this
step by step.
All right.
So, we'll start with the
tokenization.
Right? So, the goal the main thing we're
doing in the tokenization side is that
models cannot
models cannot operate on pure text.
Right? So, we sort of need to
we need to be able to create
a sort of like numerical representation
for this for the model to work off of.
And that is where tokenization comes in.
And here we'll be talking mostly about
text tokenization, but there also
similar on analogs for like different
modalities like audio and image.
So,
the process of tokenization is like a
splitting text into like a manageable
units.
And then once you have done this sort of
splitting and there's several algorithms
that
exist to find this find an effective
split and
the vocabulary associated with it. Once
[snorts] we have that, each token is
mapped to a unique integer ID, which is
essentially the index of the token in
the vocabulary that was learned or like
created.
>> [snorts]
>> And then so then the output becomes
sequence of integers representing the
sequence.
So, as you can see as visualized, we
have transformers are powerful that goes
to some black box tokenizer algorithms,
several several of which we will be
covering on a high level.
You get this sequence of tokens and you
also get
vocabulary associated like a set of
vocabulary associated with it. Right?
And then essentially
these tokens are converted to indices
through like a vocabulary lookup. And
this
this is this will go downstream for
further processing.
But mainly uh for like even you'll also
be kind of wrestling with this in your
homework four assignment is the main
trade-off. There are like some
trade-offs you have to think about when
it comes to tokenization.
One something you'll have to manage is
the vocabulary size versus sequence
length. So,
with vocabulary size like if you have
too large of a
a label space, it might be sort of more
challenging to assign probabilities to
them. Right? But then on the other hand,
attention as you might have seen in the
previous lectures,
in sequence modeling things like
attention kind of scale quadratically
with sequence length. So,
having too large of a sequence length
might not be optimal computationally.
And then you'll also have to think of
um
like handling
splits that have semantic meaning versus
how well they're able to sort of handle
out of vocabulary um
words. Right? So,
we'll
get into more of this
in as we explore some of the
tokenization methods.
Right? So, what are some tokenization
methods available to us? We have
character level tokenization. This is
pretty a naive way of doing things.
You can pretty much break down all text
into individual single characters.
Now, the advantage of this is that let's
say you're working with the English
language, so you only have 26 characters
assuming you have no numbers and stuff.
So, your vocabulary space is extremely
small and contact compact. And you're
able to essentially represent um
any words what's any word that uses
those 26 characters, right? So, you have
no risk of running into um out of you
don't have no like problems handling out
of vocabulary words thing that you
things that you did not see in the
training set.
But then the problem is that they create
massively long
sequences, right? Because um
you're splitting at the character level,
this is the worst thing you can
potentially do in terms of sequence
length. Which will then have like other
bad like downstream
effects like increasing your um
competition [snorts] time.
Right? And then there's the there's also
the problem that individual characters
like A or B, they don't really carry
much meaning.
Um like compared to like
more like
better like word sub structure
structures.
So then
we can So, the next step we could do is
we could try doing word level
tokenization. Where we split the text
like strictly by like spaces,
punctuations, or like some other
language rules.
And the downside of this is that
you're probably doing this based on your
like training set. So,
you will be creating these like um
enormous like embedding you'll be
creating this enormous potentially
creating this enormous output space.
Right? And because every variation of
like things like love, loving, and loved
kind of like
requires its own unique token instead of
being like uh
instead of like a consolidation being
happening with other sub-word
organization methods that will be seen
down the road.
And then this tokenization method also
has the problem of
that it cannot handle unseen words well.
Right? So as you'll probably be like
restricting you'll probably be creating
your vocabulary based on like some a
closed set of words in your training
set. So anything that lies out of
outside of it will not be resolved by
this method of tokenization.
And then um
but you on the flip side you each word
means something so you might be like
encoding pretty decent semantic meaning
with each token. Uh yeah and then that
is like a trade-off you'd be managing.
Right?
So that brings us to the more the most
popular algorithm for tokenization which
is used by like major models like Lama,
Gamma, and Coin 2. It is also the
tokenization
this is also the method of the sub-word
tokenization we are using for your
homework for assignments
which is byte pair encoding.
So the way it works
Do we have a question?
So how do we
So one of the questions that I see in
the chat is while tokenizing how do we
decide each value? So this kind of like
depends on the tokenization type that
we're
doing. So what I for things like
character uh
for things like character and word
you're essentially like creating like
a dictionary like a
dictionary or like a set of like um
a closed set of like uh
tokens from the get-go
from like the training set. So you can
essentially So the IDs are essentially
like the index that this particular
token resides with
within the
dictionary. But for things like byte
pair encoding we and
for other sub-word based tokenizations
what we usually do as you'll see is like
we'll start like either from like a base
collection of tokens and then we'll like
either prune or build from the ground up
like these larger and larger
token vocabularies until we like reach
um
a predefined value a predefined set of
values. Right? So that's a
that's a hyperparameter for
tokenization. So let's say you want to
create a vocabulary of 5,000 tokens. So
you set that at the beginning
and then something like BPE works by
like it uses 256 byte values as a base
and then starts uh
like iteratively merging the most
frequent pairs of
like tokens and then it so it merges
most frequent pairs assigns them to new
token IDs in the vocabulary set and then
checks if the target size has been
reached. If it hasn't been reached it
does it again. It like
then merges the next most frequent pairs
and then um
it keeps doing this iteratively until
the target size that we have set has
been reached and that creates like
So it is essentially like a frequency
based uh
tokenization and leads like longer and
longer like sub-word lengths.
I think I believe for homework four
you'll be working with like 1,000,
5,000, and 10,000 uh
vocabulary length uh
vocab sets which we trained on the uh
data set that you were like
going to be working with.
Now unigram tokenization does it the
opposite way. It starts with massive
pool of sub-words and ruthlessly prunes
the bottom 10 to 20% uh
least useful tokens.
And it has this notion of like a loss
which is sort of on a high level related
to maximizing the likelihood of the
training data set that you're choosing
and then [snorts]
so
it
essentially keeps token that maximizes
this loss. Right?
And then um
um so minimize this loss. Right? So the
good one of the So it's like a more of a
probabilistic approach to tokenization
and one of the
kind of unique things about it is that
like it can sample different
tokenizations for the exact same word at
inference time which can have sort of
regularization effect. But it is also
favored by things like the T5 model
which we'll be seeing later and Pegasus.
Right?
And then we have SentencePiece
which is essentially which which
essentially is
using which essentially uses like
unigram or byte pair encoding under the
hood but the only thing it does is that
it takes
the spacing between So it it treats
space as a unique token. So the problem
that the other tokenizers tokenization
methods have is that they implicitly
assume that words are separated by
spaces and do not take space into
account but this sort of fails for
languages like Chinese and
Japanese. So what SentencePiece does is
that it it treats the entire input as a
raw stream of bytes and take
puts the space character as a special
character in in the vocab set.
Right?
And then WordPiece is also
it's it's similar to unigram.
It's kind of like a middle ground
between unigram and byte pair encoding
where it also
merges it merges it starts from the
bottom up but it also sort of merges
pair that might like maximize the
likelihood of the training data rather
than the frequency.
So I've attached links below.
You could
read the papers. There's also cool
hugging face guides on how you would
implement this. But most of them is
usually abstracted by libraries and
traditionally when you typically when
you're working with uh
creating your own models the
main considerations you'll be making is
to like use the tokenization method that
is usually compliant with some other
piece that you have in your pipeline. So
let's say like you were using DistilBERT
for some part of your pipeline you would
um
ensure that you are using
a WordPiece
or like tokenization method for that
part of your pipeline. Or if you're
starting from the ground up you'll have
to
manage you'll have to you might want to
like just stick with something very
popular like BPE or you could just
empirically validate for your particular
use case what is the best like managing
the trade-off like a vocabulary length
and sequence length and things like
that.
All right. So in the WordPiece uh
uh
setup how do you compute the likelihood?
Um
how do you So how do So I believe in the
the exact details are So I believe that
on a high level how it works is that
you have the training data set and then
um
based on
you can calculate the probability of
seeing a particular word on the in the
training data set.
Right? And then
I believe that gives you the
original
So like using the decomposition function
that gives you the original estimate of
the likelihood and then you can
start like merging things together and
uh recompute the likelihood and see if
that increases or decreases. I believe
that it is but I'm not too sure. Right.
No no no but the point is to compute the
likelihood we need a model.
So is that just a simple
category model or do they use some kind
of a language Do they build a weak
language model?
I don't I believe I believe
SentencePiece
Sorry. I believe unigram uses a language
model but I believe they just use
WordPiece uses a category model. It
doesn't use a language model under the
hood. Okay.
Okay.
Okay. So that brings us to our first
poll question.
Which of the following is a potential
downside of uh
character level tokenization
compared to
sub-word tokenization?
Give you guys
90 seconds.
I believe is the time.
>> Do I just uh is there like uh are they
like Pokémon names or do I just randomly
pick someone here?
I want to ask this question.
No, it is just Okay.
Just ask everybody their answer in the
chat box.
Guys, what are the answers?
Oh, sorry. I jumped the gun here.
All right. So,
well, there's kind of
uh an indirect uh relationship uh kind
of based answer. So, like uh character
level
Well, I guess let's see what the answers
are.
I didn't really get
Yeah. All right. Yep, that's
uh pretty much it. So, it does not lead
to The character level the token at the
character level the vocabulary size is
going to be small because you're going
to be you're missing all the merge terms
which actually expand the vocabulary
size.
But in exchange, each sequence becomes
very long as long as the number of
characters.
Yes.
Thank you, Brad.
That's correct.
So, uh so where are we at right now? So,
we have uh this we started with text and
now we have uh this like uh sequence of
like indices like these random uh these
numbers uh which um
And then uh what's the next step? So, we
want to go from uh these sequence of uh
numbers to uh sequences of uh vectors
which we can then uh feed into the
model. And uh we want these uh vectors
to be uh to encode some sort of uh
semantic uh meaning.
So,
that is uh when we'll be uh moving to uh
we'll be moving to the embedding portion
of the uh transformer architecture.
All right. So, for your assignment,
you're just going to be using uh
nn.embedding
uh for for text. So, it's pretty much
like a learned uh lookup table uh you
maintain as uh parameter within this
like uh PyTorch class a matrix of size
uh vocab uh vocab size x
uh the embedding dimension which is uh
dimensionality of your entire model.
Um and then um essentially the uh token
ID is um just uh selects uh one row from
this uh matrix.
Uh it's just uh pure and simple uh
indic- indexing as is visualized below.
And uh you essentially the goal is for
you to jointly learn this uh embedding
um what these embeddings look like as
you're like trying to satisfy uh some
optimization objective based on your
task, right? So,
usually the idea is that this uh usually
leads to
uh these embeddings uh having encoding
some uh nice uh semantic uh geometry. Uh
so,
uh it leads to like uh them having like
some encoding some nice semantic meaning
that is relevant to your task at hand.
And then this usually manifests uh
itself as like some
uh nice like uh geometry in the
embedding space where things like uh
like uh let's say you were doing a like
uh
um
the task you're uh like working with
involves uh some notion uh of gender
like um
things that are uh in your corpus things
that are typically male related would
like cluster closer together and things
that are female related might uh cluster
together and uh things like that.
So, uh you'll be using uh essen-
nn.embedding which is uh learned lookup
table to map uh token IDs uh to a
sequence of embedding vectors. And this
uh and then we move on to the uh next
step.
Which is uh positional encoding.
So,
the main problem was that uh RNNs had uh
recurrence uh built in. So, there is uh
this inherent uh notion of order within
them. But uh there is no such uh notion
of order with the attention mechanism.
Right? Uh this is all like a position
invariant.
The attention can see all the sequence
all the sequences uh at the same time
and decide what it finds more uh most
important. So, unless you find some way
to encode uh order, uh things like the
dog uh bit the man and the man the man
the man bit the dog will essentially uh
look identical.
So, without uh
uh your model kind of like gets used to
like what different positions uh look
like. Right? If two positions look the
same,
uh that is essentially meaningless to
the model. Right? Uh it would be nice
for it to be uh deterministic. So, like
uh we can just uh compute them uh at
once from beginning and just uh cache
the values. There's uh good uh
computational um
benefits of that. All right. Um it would
also be nice if one were to be able to
uh estimate the distance between uh two
tok- tokens using this uh method of uh
positional encoding.
Using our method of positional encoding.
And uh a good uh
a good um
aspect of a positional encoding is that
one should be able to a model should be
able to extrapolate into longer
sentences. So, for example, your uh
typically when you train uh transformer
models, you set this like a fixed uh
um maximum sequence length requirement
on your model. But it would be nice if
the model was somehow able to also
extrapolate into like uh sequence
lengths that it has not
in its like uh training set that is much
larger than what it had previously
encountered.
So, the original transformer paper kind
of used this like um
sinus- sinusoidal uh based uh positional
encoding
>> [snorts]
>> uh where it used like a sine and cosine
functions at uh different frequencies
for
uh different dimensions uh to create
like a unique uh frequency for each
position.
And uh
there's uh some reasons as to why it did
that. So, this is something I believe
you'll be uh implementing for your
homework for assignment. Um
here's the equation. And essentially
what it is is that like uh for um
for positive uh for positive dimensions,
you have
uh a sinu- sinusoidal functions a series
of sinusoidal functions for uh positive
dimensions a set of sinusoidal functions
for positive dimensions. And for
uh
uh odd
not positive even. And for uh odd
dimensions, you have a set of uh cosine
functions.
Right?
And why sinusoids? Well, uh if you uh it
can be shown mathematically like uh if
you uh
compare uh uh if you calculate uh the
positional encoding of uh position plus
K,
uh you can uh uh kind of decompose this
matrix
uh using uh some trigonometric
identities and kind of show that uh
positional encoding at position plus K
is uh linear function of uh the
positional encoding at uh position.
Right? Where position is uh some
arbitrary variable that we have chosen.
Right?
Uh so, what we do is we simply uh add
these uh to our input embeddings
um to uh signify our like a notion of uh
position.
And since they have the same dimension,
they don't really increase uh the data
the dimensionality of the data. So,
that's one of the reasons of why we
don't uh concatenate also. Like you
could theoretically uh
concatenate uh these positional uh
positional embeddings
uh to the input embeddings, but then uh
you might uh you're just uh just
unnecessarily increasing uh the
computation.
So, now
um
theoretically, they should also be
scalable and should uh
theoretically uh extra- be extrapolated
extra- extrapolatable to like a longer
sequences. But that does not actually
hold in case in reality and it it can
actually uh struggle for longer sent-
sentences that it wasn't trained for.
So, this is the um
classic uh sinusoidal uh positional
encoding uh image that you see. Right?
So,
you
uh you have the embedding dimension
and the uh token position. And uh this
picture kind of kind of doesn't really
make make a lot of sense to me. So, the
more better one that I saw while making
this uh presentation was this one.
Right? So, as I mentioned uh before, so
we have
uh a series of uh sinu- uh sinusoidal
sinusoids for a set of sinusoids for
even dimensions and a set of
uh cosines for uh odd dimensions. And uh
these uh the frequency of these uh
sinusoids uh keep uh decreasing as you
go to higher dimensions.
Uh sorry, as you increase the position.
And same for the cosine.
Right? So, as as you can see
the main reason for doing this is it
kind of helps resolve ambiguities
between um
different tokens. So, as if you see here
Um sorry, these are in different
dimensions. So, like here is
visualized here is
what the values would be for position
five and position six.
Now, you can see
um
for the for the values encoded in the
higher dimensions, these are barely
distinguishable, right? This sort of
collapse to the same like position. But
in the lower dimensions,
since these values are since this is
that has more high-frequency content,
you're able to kind of distinguish
between these two two positions.
On the flip side, um
for
um
if you take a look at
position six and position 80,
um
so, if on the lower dimensions, you can
see that these kind of like position
five and position 80, you see that on
the lower dimensions, they sort of like
uh
collapse into the same value, but then
they're more distinguishable in the
higher dimensions due to the more
expanded wavelength. So, essentially,
I believe the goal of having this sort
of
um
positional encoding is that one, it is
repeatable. So, hopefully, the model can
learn
this towards the
during its training. Like hopefully,
this patterns patterns would be easy to
pick up. And then secondly, it is that
it gives like a multi-scale
view of like what positions are, right?
Because you're seeing how because of
this like changing frequencies at like
different dimensions. So, let's say
you're not able to
discern the position what the position
is from one dimension,
you hopefully the the idea is that you
might be able to discern what position
this belongs to from the information
that is encoded in the other dimensions.
If that makes sense.
Essentially, so you're getting like
multiple views of the same position.
Based on where you are at at on the
dimension size.
All right.
So, yeah. I mean, this is what we're
talking about. It brings us to our
next poll topic. In a position vector,
why are different dimensions assigned
different wavelengths?
Frequencies.
Give me 30 seconds.
All right.
Time management is
apparently not my strong suit here, so
we'll have to close the poll.
And yeah, do we have some answers?
Oh, well. I guess
again
poll management is not my strong suit as
well.
But yeah, that's
uh
that would be the answer. Like yeah, you
would allow it would allow the model to
capture patterns at different scales.
So, if you're not able to resolve
positional information from one
dimension, you could hopefully resolve
it through another.
All right.
All right. So, now what do we have here?
So, we have these sequence of embedding
vector which have been injected with
some positional information. And now
we're about
able now we're about to get into the
main bread and butter of the transformer
architecture, which is essentially going
to be like um
applications of repeated applications of
like
attention,
residual add and norm, and then
feedforward network. And this is done
through several layers. All right. So,
we'll cover the multi-head attention
mechanism real quick.
So, this is
uh
the attention operation, the scaled dot
product attention operation
you will be implementing.
And I don't know about you guys, but for
me, especially with uh
all these different variants of
attention being thrown about, you have
scaled dot product attention, multi-head
attention,
self-attention,
cross-attention,
it can get hard to keep track track of
things. So, hopefully, we can work
towards resolving that ambiguity.
All right. So,
scaled dot product attention is the core
operation, right? So, given some query
key value matrices,
you when somebody says they're applying
scaled dot product attention on it, this
is the core operation.
>> [snorts]
>> Right? And you'll also be implementing
this for your homework four, right?
Um
So, essentially,
so the way to look at look at it is like
in
general computer science, you're
essentially doing like when you do
things like database lookups, you're
doing like a hard lookup. So, you have
set of keys,
each key has with it value assigned to
it
in things like, you know, document
databases or key-value databases, right?
And then given a query, you sort of do
like a hard lookup to find out which key
is
which key is an exact match, and then
you procure the associated value.
But uh
in
our field of deep learning, we have
what we do is that we do a soft lookup.
So,
this has the advantage of it being
differentiable, and we can get a
weighted sum of values based on how
correlated or how similar the query is
to the particular key.
And this notion of similarity
correlation manifests in different ways
depending on what
what the query and keys are, which as
we'll see later.
And we'd also want each token weights to
sum to one, which is why we use the
softmax.
Keeps things nice and bounded, right?
All right. So,
here again is so, we have our So, this
is the I believe uh
the self-attention version of it, but
don't get too bogged down on that aspect
of it. So, we have
at the input sequence, we do a linear
projection to get our query vec query
matrix,
again a linear projection to get the key
matrix, and the linear projection to get
our
value mat matrix, right? So,
essentially, what self what we're doing
in self-attention is we're trying to see
how important each like what's the
importance of
uh
the other parts of a sequence. Like
we're trying to weight how much how
important each sequence is to itself,
right? Each portion of a sequence is to
itself. So, what what I mean by that is
let's say
um
have a word, my name is
his name is
like Alex. So, how important is like So,
when we
are trying to like make some
determination about like words like I
That's not a great example, but you
could um
use a better sentence, but we're trying
to essentially weight how important each
token is to the other tokens that
surround it, right? That's the
self-attention portion of it. So, that's
why we're using That's why the query
vectors is the input vector itself.
Right?
And you're we're trying to compare the
self-importance within different parts
of the input sequence.
Right?
So, then we take a soft So, we have
So, Q shape will be we're ignoring the
batch dimension for now. It'll be a
sequence length times D D model.
K will also be a sequence length times D
model, although they do not have to be
the same sequence. You do a transpose,
do a
matrix multiplication, you scale by
uh
the square root of D.
Why we do that, we'll cover that in a
bit. And you get this like and you take
a softmax to sort of get this like
attention scores.
And you can see here in a French to
these
attention weights usually have like
really nice sometimes collapse into
these nice like interpretable
probability properties. You'll also see
this when we do when you do homework
four. You'll this will
be like a big debugging strategy when
you do homework four. Like
you will want to see So, in this
particular case, you can see there's
like
sort of like um
sequential relationship between French
and English. But for
this particular set of words, um
like it has to rely on um
there's a
it's not just a one-to-one relationship.
There's like
for certain words
more weights are assigned to like set of
words in the input sequence.
You'll also see this in um
in the speech transform the automatic
speech recognition
task that we're doing for homework four.
So for example,
I'm speaking and my speed of the speech
and sorry, my speech is mapped to this
like
transcript, but my speech does not like
there's not like a one-to-one
correspondence between my like discrete
speech tokens and
the tokens on the word. So one thing
you'll want to figure out is to see that
oh like if your model is picking up on
the inherent like sequential nature
secret inherent like sequential mapping
between like my voice and the text. If
it if it isn't, then that means like
there's a bug in your model. And I
believe this will be covered in homework
four as well.
Right, so
why is the dot product
not enough? So
assuming
So the main problem is that like um
if you recall the softmax function, so
assuming that Q and K
this can be derived if you go I believe
there's a better derivation in the
link below. But um
assuming key Q and K are like zero mean
and unit variance,
you can show that um
the
um
variance of um
the product is essentially all of DK.
Um and then if you recall the softmax
operation like things can get
really flattened at the as values
become too arbitrarily large or too
arbitrarily small. So there's not really
enough gradient information. Um
as values get too larger too small. So
to kind of rescale these values
into like a more manageable region of
the softmax
function,
we take um
we take the we scale by DK.
But there's like there's a nice
mathematical proof about why this is
good also in the
link below.
Right?
So that that's essentially the scale dot
product attention
operation.
Um but
um
this is just that so essentially the
in in our transform models what we use
is we use multi-head attention, which is
essentially doing scale dot product
attention repeatedly. Right? So the idea
is that um
there might be many different ways in
which query might react with a key in
like different contexts
to capture sort of different kinds of
relationships. So there might be like
different notions of similarity. Right?
And in order to be able to model that,
we use this thing called multi-head
attention.
So if you can if you see our picture
here
so instead of one large attention pass
we
split we split this into different heads
and then each head does its like own
projection, its own like
scale dot product attention
operation.
Um and then we compute the output
independently and finally everything is
concatenated and passed through the
final weight matrix to get the final
result, right? The weighted average of
the value matrix, right?
So
that is essentially what that is the
multi-head attention operation.
So we'll be doing a quick comparison
here. So
it can be
now although we have these different
linear layers, you in practice you don't
really need all these linear layers and
this can be achieved by like using one
linear layer and doing like a split and
um
transpose
as which essentially gives does the same
thing as we'll be seeing in the next
slide.
Right? So scale
dot product attention is pretty simple.
You have query
mat mul K transpose and then this is
again mat mulled with the values to get
the final output.
Now here's oh sorry,
skip this up. So we have the input. We
project to query key and value matrices
and then we do the scale dot product
attention. So this is essentially just a
single head attention.
Right? But for multi-head, what we do is
we decompose this like
the embedding dimension
into like head times DH and then we
reshape this and we transpose this where
the head essentially becomes like
another sort of like batch dimension
per se, right? And then um
so you have these different heads of
query key and value matrices
to which to
each of this you can just apply scale
dot product attention in one go to each
and um
then once you've done once you've done
this, you can then re-transpose things
back. So we go from BHLDH
to BLHDH
and then we merge these.
So this is the concatenation operation I
was talking about. We just merge the
heads and the dimensions again to come
back to our BLDK.
And then we do the final again we have a
output projection layer
and we get our final output.
So it's essentially this is the
pretty much equivalent to like um
this whole like split head operation and
concat head operation is essentially
like equivalent to like applying
several different like linear layers.
Right?
And you'll be implementing this for your
homework four assignment.
Right?
So
So that's the multi-head attention. But
then there are various types of
multi-head attention used in the
attend in the transform model. So if we
take a look at the this is
sort of the classic encoder-decoder
transform model
that was presented in the 2017 paper.
And um
on the encoder side, you are allowed to
attend to each token is allowed to
attend to every other token. So right so
there's this bidirectional nature. I
believe you would do the same thing when
you were creating your RNN
encoder-decoder architectures. You would
you'd want there to be like
there's no like
no notion of cheating, right? So there's
no like
causality constraint. So you would want
um
each token to
attend to all the other tokens in the
input sequence to create that
to create a good representation.
Right? So on the encoder side, we use
this
we use a bidirectional attention. So
what that what what I mean by that is
like every token
is allowed to attend to every other
token. So there's really no like masking
involved or things like that.
But on the decoder side, we're sort of
we still
at inference time we still want to
generate things auto-regressively,
right? So
um
at least during training when you're
doing things like teacher forcing, you
don't want to like cheat and
look ahead on the answers or else you'll
just pretty much be doing like copy
paste of like the
teacher forced input to the output.
Right? So to enforce that, we um
enforce this masking to the scale dot
product attention operation. So
essentially you're not
the model is not allowed to like look
ahead and and generation is purely
conditioned on like
the
what the input is at the current time
step and everything before it, right?
So that's the those are the two forms of
masking here. So you have the no mask
method which is bidirectional and then
you have a causal mask that is
applied on the decoder side to um
like prevent any sort of cheating during
the
inference time during train time, sorry.
Right?
And then you have this form of attention
which we'll call cross attention where
which we'll discuss more in the next
slide where your
where
let's just go to the next slide. Right?
So
here's the difference between self
attention cross attention. So [snorts]
you'll be working with both aspects of
it. Right? So when you're working on
your homework for part one,
you do not have
you're not doing any sort of conditional
generation, right? You're
pretty much doing like next token
completion. So [snorts] there you're
purely using self attention. So you want
to
sort of
Yes, homework four is really spicy.
So you'll sort of like
want to weigh what each input
token means to itself with respect to
other the other input tokens, right?
So all your query key and value come
from the input sequence itself to get
like
um
appropriately weighted uh
of the input sequence.
Uh but for uh cross-attention, so let's
say you have uh
uh you're we're doing this the ASR uh
task, right? The automatic speech
recognition task. We have We are going
from uh speech to uh text. So, we want
to be able to sort of
uh
query like uh for a given text, uh which
speech tokens are most relevant for this
uh given uh word uh query. So, for that
purpose, your query comes from the uh
decoder side, and your uh key and values
are the encoded output. So, then for
each uh query,
um
you're able to find the appropriately
weighted parts of the uh encoded
sequence. And that is what uh
cross-attention is.
So,
yeah. So, self-attention uh is when all
QKV all originate from the same input
sequence, and cross-attention is uh when
you're doing uh things like uh
uh
uh conditional generation,
um like things like uh neural machine
translation and uh ASR, where you're
generating uh based on some uh condition
on some encoded representation. Um
the query uh comes from the decoder,
while key and value comes from the uh
encoder.
Yep. Uh self-attention is to help a word
understand its own context, while the
cross-attention is to help a word
understand uh the context of the speech
that it is like uh being conditioned to
generate on.
Right? So,
for the uh ASR case.
Right?
So, uh here's a cool example. I believe
it was shared with by
uh Shrey uh last semester.
So, you can see uh how um
kind of uh the cross-attention,
like how different parts of the
um attention map uh change based on like
the uh query.
So, I believe uh what Shrey was trying
to highlight here was um
uh you can see how like uh there seems
to be like uh some sort of like uh
semantic correspondence between the word
that is being uh said here and the
region of the image that is being
focused on. For example, when you say
bear, like uh there's a
big [snorts]
uh weight focus on like the overall
shape of the bear. When you say watches,
there's like uh big weight focus on like
the region where the eyes of the bear
are. And when you say bird, like there's
supposedly a big uh weight focus on the
bird in the image. But, um
you'll also see this in our homework
four assignment, where like uh
um you'll see the sort of like uh
like I said, the the speed which with I
speak and uh
to my speech and my words are at a
different uh scale. Right? So, you'll
see how like uh my um
uh
uh the word I say will like map to like
multiple portions of my speech, and
you'll get this like uh nice uh
like a sequential uh relationship uh in
the like roughly sequential relationship
in the cross-attention maps.
All right. Uh that brings us to the uh
feed-forward layers.
Uh this is uh pretty standard
uh
just an MLP, right? Uh I believe in the
main model in the original paper, they
just uh
uh they would
uh uh do a projection to four times
dimensional. So, essentially, the goal
is if you've been noticing this whole uh
uh like a lecture, there's not a lot of
uh nonlinearities in the uh whole
transformer attention, like minus the
softmax, but that's doing its own thing.
So,
the goal of this uh feed-forward uh
block is to essentially like uh increase
like the um modeling capabilities of the
model by adding uh uh some additional
nonlinearities, and that this was like
all like, you know, empirically
validated by them. Right? So,
uh in the model, um they
uh they do this like uh uh expand and uh
contract uh thing, where they
uh increase dimensionality by uh four
times by projecting by doing this a
projection, then they apply this
nonlinearity, and then they come back to
the original
uh D model uh dimensions.
All right.
Pretty straightforward pretty uh
straightforward. And then uh so, you
have all these add and norm operations,
right? Um which is uh the crux of uh the
uh attention um architecture again.
So,
essentially, uh this is a kind of
similar to the uh residual uh add norm
that you've already been doing on uh in
the CNNs.
So,
each layer has uh residual connection
and normalization layer. So, you uh take
a residual connection here, you add it
to the output of the uh multi-head
attention, and then you do uh layer
norm. You also do this on the uh
feed-forward side as well.
And uh empirically, what they saw is
that uh
what this enabled uh for them is that
they were able to train uh deeper
networks, and uh this also uh led for uh
more uh stable training.
Important thing to note is that uh in
transformer,
um and mostly in like N M NLP-based
stuff, there's this over prevalence of
like uh layer norm, which is uh
kind of similar to batch norm, but then
the statistics are like the mean
variance statistics are calculated along
the uh embedding dimension instead of
the uh batch dimension.
Right? Uh there are uh two variants of
the uh transformer
uh two variants of the uh transformer
architecture. We have the uh pre-norm uh
variant and the post-norm variant. And I
believe in the assignment, you'll be uh
implementing the pre-norm variant. So,
which is kind of the uh more modern like
uh
it was a more uh modern twist on the old
architecture. So, it's the only the only
difference is you're just uh taking the
uh norm at a different uh step. Right?
So,
uh so, here you have you do the uh you
take the residual before the layer norm.
Right? And then uh you then you do a
layer norm before going to the
multi-head attention uh in the pre-norm
architecture. And then in the post-norm
architecture,
uh you do the residual add first, and
then go to the layer norm.
Uh and yeah,
um
uh in our FT ablations, essentially like
the pre-norm architecture was just much
more easier to train, so that's really
the
one we've been uh we assigned to you
for homework four to build up.
Right? And then uh after all this, we
just have a final uh so, like uh if
we're doing a next uh sequence uh next
uh token prediction task, uh we have
we'll need to be able to go from this uh
D model space to our uh vocabulary
space. So, we'll just we'll have this uh
final projection layer, which will just
be another linear layer, uh to which we
uh out uh then to which we apply uh
softmax to create like uh
uh probability distribution over the
vocabulary space.
And uh what we do is uh we then take the
uh embedding um take the take the vector
as the at the last time step, and we
interpret that to be the probability of
uh the next token conditioned on
everything else that came before it. And
uh yeah, and then there's uh you have
your whole way of like decoding using
either like greedy or beam search or
like uh random sampling and uh top P top
K sampling and stuff like that.
All right. So, that's the uh
transformation
um architecture in a nutshell. Right?
And this this is something you'll also
be going uh pretty deep into uh in your
homework four uh assignment.
All right.
And uh
So, we have a question here. Let me see.
Okay, so we have a question
uh about why pre-norm often performs
better than uh post-norm. So, I believe
uh
Uh well, there's uh I So, this I most of
this was through uh empirical uh
validation, but I believe the argument
was that like uh it uh prevents like uh
extreme uh activations by sort of like
uh normal normalizing the input uh
before uh like uh processing it. So,
kind of like each layer then kind of
gets like uh well-behaved like inputs.
Uh which hopefully should lead to
uh
better like uh convergence. But, on the
uh post-norm side, you kind of have to
like uh tweak things harder and like uh
tweak the learning rate uh
tweak the warm-up scheduling and
uh do like some careful like
hyperparameter uh tuning to sort of like
avoid this uh training instability,
which uh sort of vanishes when you go to
the uh pre-norm architecture.
>> [snorts]
>> But, uh the original uh so, it is
possible to like uh you know, uh train
and get good like uh the original paper
was post-norm, and then it is possible
to get uh good performance with
post-norm. It just uh
it was just more harder to like uh set
the hyperparameters, I believe. You need
the right set of hyperparameters for uh
good convergence.
All right.
Okay. So, everything together, we have
our final transformer architecture.
All right.
We have a poll.
Which I will keep to
>> We have 10 more minutes. Just, you know,
Yeah, sounds good.
Uh, 30 seconds on this.
Which which of the following is true
about
self-attention?
To put the
All right.
You can take a look at the Can get some
answers in the chat.
I feel like a feel like a streamer.
Perfect. Yes, it is 1 3 4. Um, attention
weights The only incorrect option is
attention weights are squared scaled by
square root of D instead of dimension D.
All right. So, I'm about to blaze
through the remaining portion of
this as much as I can.
So,
there have been some modern improvements
to the
transformer architecture. So, we have
first the overall um
uh, architecture uh
design, right? So, you can have like
this is the similar to RNN RNNs. You can
can have encoder-decoder attention. Uh,
encoder-decoder transformers,
decoder-only transformers like chat GPT
like GPT-2 or 3, I believe. And then you
have encoder-only transformers like
BERT.
Right? So,
encoder-decoder uh, transportation
Encoder-decoder transformers are
typically the architecture you go for
when you are like doing some generation
conditioned [snorts] on like something
conditioned on like something else. For
example, like
the sequence-to-sequence models for like
uh
uh, the text-to-text models. So, like
translating from like English to German
or like um
just translating from speech to text.
Things like that, you'd use like
encoder-decoder
architecture. The T5 architecture is
a very famous architecture and uh
essentially it's been trained to handle
various NLP tasks.
I
like and uh
uh, the which task it is currently doing
engaged in can be like sort of
controlled via
what's uh
the tokens that are present in the
prompt. Right? So,
uh, this would be a good paper to read
for that.
Uh, then we have encoder-only
architectures where essentially
uh, we are uh
uh, just um
We only have an encoder model, right?
The goal essentially is to learn like
good representations, which will be
somewhat applicable to downstream tasks,
right? So, that is the main like it's
sort of like a sort of representation
learning. Uh, where you want to learn
good representation, which you can
leverage for downstream tasks. So, for
BERT, the idea is that the BERT
embeddings encode like good semantic
meaning.
And they learn this through their
training strategy, which was a
combination weighted combination of
masked token prediction, where
essentially um
uh, given
their the goal of the BERT
model was to predict tokens.
Uh, predict tokens in the masked regions
given conditioned on what other token
conditioned on the unmasked tokens.
Right? And then they also do next
sentence prediction. So,
given two sentences,
they also
um, like the label is like one if uh
uh, the sentences naturally follow one
another or not. So, the BERT has to make
that determination as well. And then um
the goal of that, I believe, was to for
the BERT to like get a good local
understanding of language and also have
like a broader more global understanding
of language as well. And then
so, BERT embeddings tend to be these
like semantically rich embeddings, which
can then be leveraged to which can then
serve as like feature representations
for more downstream tasks.
Right? Um
So, this is the pre-training and
fine-tuning paradigm. So, like you
pre-train on this proxy task to get like
general level language understanding.
And then you can fine-tune using those
embeddings on downstream tasks like
machine learning and question answering.
Right? So,
then you have decoder-only language
models like GPT.
They're purely trained to predict the
next token conditioned on the previous
tokens. Right?
Uh, and then um
the large language models are
essentially like scaling this up, right?
So, scaling this up to like bigger
um
um, to larger data sets like adding like
multimodal capabilities and even adding
things like tool use and things like
that. So, that's the progression of like
GPT through through the years.
All right.
Um
So,
there was some so, there are some
problems with
the positional encoding design. So,
one of the problems that we noticed with
the sinusoidal
uh um
positional encoding was that like it
doesn't really extrapolate well to like
sequence lengths not in the training
set. So, like for larger sequence
lengths. So, to a lot of work has been
done to sort of find like better uh
um
sort of find a positional
encodings that extrapolate better. So,
towards that that end, we have like
positional encoding types like rotary,
T5 bias, and Alibi, which don't really
work
the
you're not really adding anything to the
input, but you're essentially adding
encodings or like you're modifying the
um
uh, key and the queries the query and
the values in the attention mechanism.
Um
And they do they both approach it like
things like Alibi, T5 bias, they
approach it in different ways, but
they've been shown to essentially have
like um
better extrapolation capabilities. And
you could read about those in their
corresponding papers.
All right.
So,
one big problem with attention is
that it does have like it does scale
quadratically with sequence length. And
although
like uh
computation it's good for um
it's good for like
things like GPUs because you can pretty
much like stuff it all in like one go.
And
the entire operation is massively
parallelizable. But then there's still
like
there's still a bottleneck and uh
like it would be there have been a lot
of work to like sort of kind of get rid
of this bottleneck or like reduce the
bottleneck.
One
is the famous quadratic complexity that
the attention has based on sequence
length.
Uh, so there have been several different
types of attention that have been
developed to sort of combat this or like
reduce the impact that this bottleneck
has to improve
competition. One very famous one is
FlashFlash attention, which is
essentially the same attention you get
the same attention output, but it is a
more IO-aware algorithm. So,
if you are familiar with the storage
hierarchy in computers, you have
an L1 cache compared to So, like
data reads and writes in L1 caches are
much more faster than say reads and
writes to disk. Right? So, similar
hierarchy also exists in GPUs, where you
have a GPU SRAM, which is which has much
faster read and writes compared to like
the GPU HBM or main memory. And
essentially the goal of this algorithm
is to essentially constrain our read and
writes to the GPU SRAM.
Um
And the way it does this through like
through this like tiled
tiled computation of the attention
mechanism and then this online softmax
algorithm. And that leads to essentially
like a
a
2.8 uh
um, times speed up compared to just
naive attention.
Uh, but it's you get the same output.
Then another form of
optimization, which you can also
actually explore in homework four if you
want to
like speed up your training, is you
could do this thing called
key-value caching, right? So,
recomputing the key and value
So, this is something you can do to
speed up your inference, right? So,
instead of computing
values at
instead of recomputing key and
your key and values, you can just cache
them.
And uh
uh, so all you're doing is you're
you're you're essentially going to use
the query vector to compute the key and
the value vector for that particular
time step.
And then you don't really have to You
don't have to essentially you don't have
to like recompute this QKT step. You can
just
use keep a like a cache of like key
vectors and then just multiply the query
with them query with it to get just a
portion of the uh
uh attention score which you can then
concatenate to the value.
Uh it's pretty straightforward. Uh you
can take a look at this link here. It's
pretty easy to implement too. Uh
definitely recommend it if you want to
speed up your inference time especially
when you're doing things like a beam
search with like a big uh beam width.
>> [snorts]
>> Uh I believe this might have to be the
last poll.
Last poll question.
Um I really didn't get a chance to cover
flash attention well.
Uh but
hopefully I covered the aspect of flash
attention which is relevant to this
poll.
I will
I will end this poll
before time runs out.
So All right.
Thank you guys.
You have the answers guys?
You get some answers?
Okay.
There's two. Okay, flash attention is
two.
>> Perfect, right?
Anyway, let's uh
uh we have uh a bunch of topics left
over here but they should be on the
slides.
Uh I'd like to thank Puru for an
excellent lecture. The stuff he did
cover was covered in great detail.
Uh and uh so please everybody give him a
big hand.
On Wednesday we have
we have uh Omar Khattab doing a lecture.
Omar of course there's a professor at
CMU he's got to use with a lot of uh
excellent work on
on AI and large language models. So
please do attend.
Thank you all.